All praise is due to Allah, and I bear witness that there is no deity except Allah, alone,
He has no partner, and I bear witness that Muhammad is His servant and Messenger.
may Allah’s peace and blessings be upon him. To proceed: welcome and greetings
to you all in the first session of this new series,
the new series of reflection, this new course,
which we have titled: “Lessons I Learned from Prophet Yusuf, peace be upon him,” or,
we may call it: Reflections on Surah Yusuf, peace and blessings be upon him
and upon our Prophet.
So we ask Allah to open for us the doors of goodness,
and to guide us to every good,
and to accept from us and from you righteous deeds.
And to help us to understand this
الصوره الحقيقه هو يعني الكلام مش مش
Exaggeration makes a person feel very burdened, meaning burden
It is really big and it is inside the picture because it is
Not like any picture, God described it in the best stories
The subject requires a lot of effort from us, sorry
In the name of God
The subject takes a lot of effort from us.
We ask God for success and facilitation
And may God grant success. Amen, God willing. Amen.
All
As usual
Which Surah do we start with?
الاول بنستفتح بالقراءه عشان ناخد بركه
Read the Quran and then we sit and chat.
The meanings and aesthetics of the Surah
Surah
Joseph, peace be upon him, and this is the first meeting
Let's start reading first
We seek help from God Almighty
Let's start with the beneficial effects.
We will read, God willing
I think today we can take from the verse
one
To verse six, only six verses we will live with in
First meeting
I seek refuge in God from Satan the accursed
In the name of God, the most gracious, the most merciful
pain
These are the verses of the clear Book.
I
Anzalnah
Our Qur’an is in Arabic so that you may understand.
We relate to you the best of stories in what We have revealed to you.
Here is the Quran
And if you were before that among the heedless
When Joseph said to his father, “O my father, indeed I have seen someone
planet
The sun and the moon
And the sun and the moon, I showed them prostrating to me.
He said, my son
Do not tell your brothers about your dream, lest they plot against you.
The devil is for man
A clear enemy
And thus your Lord chooses you and teaches you
From the interpretation of hadiths
May His blessings and mercy be upon you and upon
Al Jacob as
Atoms
on
Your parents before Abraham
Wassaq
These
Your Lord is All-Knowing and All-Wise
Surah Yusuf, peace be upon him, the truth about man
He is advancing, meaning between these pictures, with all awe.
You deserve it
Surah Yusuf, peace be upon him
Let's get to know the surah. First, it is a Meccan surah.
The Makki Surah is not the same as the other one.
Surah Makkih
It was revealed to the Prophet, may God bless him and grant him peace, and God
Come on, I know, in the most difficult period of the Meccan decade
All of it is the period that was between
The death of Khadija and the death of Abu Talib and the pledge of allegiance at Aqaba
First
وهي الفتره اللي هي عام الحزن من عام
Sadness until we reach the first obstacle
This is the most difficult period that the Prophet, peace and blessings be upon him, has gone through.
Peace be upon you
And behind it are very, very severe trials.
ابتلاقات كانت زادت قوي طبعا كان ده
Shortly before that, the Prophet, may God bless him and grant him peace,
Peace be upon you from the people of Abu Talib and the people of Abu
طالب اللي هجروا فيه اخواته اللي هجروا
فيه اعمامه اللي هجروا فيه يعني الناس
اللي منه تمام اقاربه ما من قريش وكان
نزلت سوره يوسف عشان تقول له لو كان
Your brothers from Quraish did this to you and made you enter a tribe
Abu Talib and his brother Yusuf worked in 1 A 3 and it was
Surah Yusuf is a consolation for the heart of the Prophet, peace be upon him
والسلام وبتقول له نهايه يوسف عليه السلام
It was empowerment and his sisters repented in the end
وانصلح حالهم وكان دي كانت بشاره للنبي
عليه الصلاه والسلام ان نهايه الابتلاء ده
Enable in the end and one can not even
He is afflicted
ونهايه الالم ده يعني سعه وسرور وفرج من
God Almighty
وبشار ليه ان زي ما اخوات يوسف يعني يعني
تابوا في النهايه فالله سبحانه وتعالى
يبشره ان اللي عمل فيك كده في شعب ابي
Student, God willing
يتوبوا وينصلح حالهم وده اللي حصل بالفعل
After the conquest of Mecca, this means just getting to know
The beautiful Surah
Surah Yusuf, peace be upon him
It is said that the reason for its revelation is that
The companions, may God be pleased with them, said:
To the Prophet, may God bless him and grant him peace, meaning they were
They were bored and wanted some stories. They said, “Oh…”
Messenger of God, did you tell us stories? I mean, if there is none
كده مواعظ جوه قصص يعني ايه وده يدل على
The importance of stories in preaching. The Companions themselves, may God be pleased with them.
الله عنهم وارضاهم طلبوا من النبي عليه
Peace and blessings mean that he tells many stories because of his strength.
The effect of the story on the heart and soul, so he said, O Messenger of God
God, why don’t you tell us about it? Then He revealed His words, “We”
We relate to you the best of stories, and Surah Yusuf was revealed to him.
Peace be upon the hearts of the companions and the Prophet, peace be upon him.
Peace and blessings for the tremendous impact of the story on
النفس وقوه الوعظ اللي بيبقى دايما في
The story is that it provides a practical model all the time.
Far from theorizing, it is a practical model that is immediately presented.
I advise you through real practical experience.
Glory be to God, that is why Surat Al-Qasas is a surah.
Joseph, peace be upon him, is one of the amazing images called
Surah Yusuf, peace be upon him, is a consolation for every sad person.
سلوى كل محزون ما في احد عنده مشكله ولا
No sadness, no distress, no worries, it doesn't mean anything
You imagine that it happened in your life, in the story of Joseph
Peace be upon him, no one passes by this story
الا ويجد فيها بغيته ويجد فيها الطمانينه
He finds peace and comfort in it.
اجابات كتيره جدا على اسئله كتيره جدا
يمكن يعني مش عايز اضرب امثله دلوقتي عشان
Don't rush until you finish the picture with me, God willing.
الله هتنبهروا قد ايه الصوره دي جاوبت على
Every question is on the mind of each one of us. Come on.
Let's open up after we get to know the picture
And with its beauty we open and say, O Lord, help us and guide us
To ponder this beautiful and noble Surah
Okay, the surah begins with “In the name of God, the Most Gracious, the Most Merciful.”
pain
particle for direct object
This blessed Surah begins like many Surahs.
Mecca B
In the disconnected letters and the disconnected letters are words
كتير قوي في الحروف المقطعه لكن يعني اشهر
Two sayings about the disconnected letters
The first saying
The letters are DATE, each letter represents a word.
وده كان قول ابن عباس رضي الله عنه وارضاه
He used to say Alif Lam Ra, meaning I am God, I see
I see God
And no, God knows best, so I told him that everything
A letter that indicates a word. What is the benefit of Ibn Ijtihad?
Abbas, may God be pleased with him and many of the companions
Kabi Bakr, Omar and others were stopping in
These letters stop at these letters that
القول الثاني واللي اختاره شيخ الاسلام
Ibn Taymiyyah, may God have mercy on him, said that these letters
But it was brought for a purpose and for a reason, meaning it may not be
It has meaning in itself but there is a greater purpose.
من ورائها ايه الغايه العظيمه اللي من
Behind these letters
Come imagine with me
To whom was this Quran revealed? We revealed it.
Our Quran is in Arabic, right? It was revealed to the Arabs in the first place.
It was first revealed to the Arabs and of course it was revealed to the worlds, but...
The first thing that came down was the Arabs and the Arabs at the time
They were almost the strongest generation in history.
In Arabic
At that time, the Arabs had the strongest craftsmanship.
It is their language
Rather, markets were held for the purpose of competition.
Poetry and sometimes wars were waged for the sake of
بيت شعر وممكن يحصل صلح ببيت شاعر
Satire can turn the world upside down, and praise can turn it upside down.
The world was their merchandise, the poet and the prose
والتنافس في الباب ده رهيبه لدرجه من شده
The competition has reached the peak of strength in language.
والقاعده بتقول ان صاحب الصنعه تلفته
Craftsmanship means if you or you are now one
He understands Arabic very well, he is the best one in
The world is in the Arab world, you are in the transportation
تمام راكب اتوبيس فالناس ده بيتكلم في
الطماطم وده بيتكلم في الخيار وده بيتكلم
In gold, you are not focused anymore. It will be lost in two.
بيتكلموا في العربيات هتعمل ايه انت تلاقي
What's wrong with you? You traveled all the time. You, for example, A
You love makeup a lot, for example, and you are distinguished in it.
الباب ده وفاهمانه قوي فيه وحافظه كل حاجه
فيه انت قعدتي في في ميكروباس ولا بتاع دي
This lady talks about cooking and this one talks about…
I'm not focusing on the kids, I found two
بيتكلموا في الميك اب وماركاته هتلاقي
ودانك ايه راعت معاهم على طول صح حتى لما
We all entered the same place
هتلاقي بتاع النجف بيبص في النجفه بتاع
Ceramics is looking for ceramics and stuff
The sofas are made by the owner
Craftsmanship provokes and attracts him, so put yourself in a man's place
عربي قح صنعته اللغه مره واحده بيجي له
كده واحد بيقول ل را هيعمل ايه؟ ام هيروح
Wrap it all around, without thinking about wrapping it around
How long is this? What's new? What's this?
ايه عايز تقول ايه يعني ايه ط س م ايوه
What do you want to say? He pulls hard and listens.
اللي جاي وبالتالي هو ده المطلوب ان هو
He hears what is coming and makes sure that this is the Quran
From the All-Wise, All-Knowing
The second need
It is after I drew attention with letters
The section
The second wisdom of including the letters is that this is…
Challenge, challenge to the Arab man, I say to him
God was sending him an implicit message that the speech
اللي انت هتسمعه ده اللي جاي اللي مش
You will know how to bring something like it
Of the letters you actually speak
We did not come with strange letters, but it is the Alif
Alif, Lam, Ra, Ta, Seen, and Meem
The Kaff, the Haa, the Yaa, the Ain and the Sad are
Your letters are the letters that you make from them
The speech is good, this is the speech of the Lord of the Worlds, if you bring
زيه يبقى ده مش كلام رب العالمين
طبعا ده تحدي رهيب بالنسبه للرجل عربي
بيستفزه جدا انت عارف عامل زي ايه
When you want to make someone disabled and you want to show him that
انت ما تعرفش تعمل اللي انا بعمله تروح
اعمل ايه؟ تروح رمي له الادوات قدامه تقول
He has tools. Take all the tools. Take my tools too.
Come on, give me the tools and show me how clever you are.
You know what to do. You know how to do the same as me.
I'm still talking to you, for example, I don't know
You act like me, so you admit that you are incapable of being you
It works like him and the higher issue means it is fine
We win the letters, take Alif, Lam, and Ra
And the letters Ta, Seen, and Meem, show me what you will do with them
What are your letters? I did not bring new letters.
الاخر هتسمع دلوقتي بعد الحروف دي كلام مش
You will know how to bring something like it, but you will not know how to bring a hadith like it.
Never, the challenge is still on. Let them come up with a picture like mine.
They come with a hadith like mine and they come with ten fabricated images.
If you do not do it, and you will never do it even if all of humanity gathers together
And the jinn are not able to produce the like of this Qur’an.
They come up with something similar, a challenge that will remain until the Day of Resurrection.
رجل عربي يقدر يجيب زي النص ده يبقى احنا
liars
Ok, of course, if the generation is the first generation
The one who is the most skilled generation in the language is unable to remain
باب اولى تضيع وقت ان اللي بعده يحاول لان
After him, I will be unable to face this challenge. Do you understand?
The idea
والجيل الاول اعترف كانوا بيعترفوا بينهم
They are not able to bring someone like him, and he told them
He says that he has a sweetness that he used to tell them, he says, oh
People, by God, I have learned poetry, but it is not poetry
And We have taught the eagle, and it is not an eagle, and that it has
لحلاوه وان عليه لطلاوه وان اعلاه لمثمر
Its bottom is abundant, and it rises high and nothing rises above it.
فكان الحروف دي بتخلص موضوع كبير قوي ايه
What do you end the topic with? What do you end the topic with?
The Quran is the word of God. Imagine that the matter is over.
بالحروف دي الحروف دي خلصت
A very big topic, meaning it should be followed by letters.
دي شويه الرجل العربي يسلم ويقر ان ده
The word of the Lord of the Worlds, and the argument against him ends.
It is sufficient for him that We have sent down to you the Book which is recited
Indeed in that is mercy and a reminder for a people who believe.
هم كانوا بيطلبوا الايات فربنا بيقول هو
مش مكفيهم الايه دي طب عديها الاول بعد
So let's talk, you didn't pass it, so you didn't
Don't ask for anything new before you send me the verse.
وما عدهاش كده كده يبقى انت كده كده
If you are stubborn, then there is no need for me to give you
الايات اللي انت بتقترحها فهمنا الفكره
So the second statement is that he believes that the letters
This clip was just meant to get the man's attention.
This attracts attention. The second thing
لتحدي الرجل العربي واستفزازه علشان يسمع
وعشان يظن ان هو يقدر يجيب زيه فيقهر وفي
The end means he is convinced that he can never do it.
To come with a verse like this? The Quran is this?
سبب في استجابته واسلامه بعد كده هم نفسهم
العرب من شده حبهم للغه كانوا بيستخبوا
At night, they hear the Prophet, peace and blessings be upon him.
وهو بيصلوا بيصلي وكانوا بيقابلوا بعض
ويقعدوا يعدبوا بعض يقول له انت ايه اللي
Who brought you here? He says, "Sorry, I couldn't. I'm coming."
Listen to this beautiful Arabic saying to me
Someone comes here to meet him the next day and the third day
They meet, it's something very strange. I love the letters.
المقطعه اللي هي بتكثر جدا في السور
Mecca in particular and you will find that there is a very clear need that
بعد الحروف المقطعه دي على طول بياتي ذكر
القران لازم او عاده بص للام بعديها بيجي
Because these letters are supposed to end the Quran
With God for the mothers. That is the Book about which there is no doubt.
These are the verses of the clear Book. Ta-Sam-Sam. These are the verses of the clear Book.
Verses of the clear Book Ha A Mim. By the Book
Download the book from God, the Almighty, the Wise
You will always find this because Date connects me to Date
This is a book revealed by God, the Almighty, the Wise.
We understand the brands
The clear book told you that is a sign to the distant, right?
I tell you this and that
This is a reference to something far away, but the point is that this
The Quran is so high, so powerful, so sublime, so powerful that you cannot reach it.
You do not know how to answer it completely. It is a precious book. So, may it be high.
شان القران عبر عن علو هذا الشان وارتفاعه
About the Arabic language, referring to something far away
ايات كل ايه تعتبر داله على وحدانيه الله
Understanding the verses, verses, every light, verses, you will enter into it and you will find
It confuses you and you find that it indicates the one Lord
The Kind, the All-Knowing, the verses of the clear book mean
It is not an obscure book, but rather a clear book.
Clearly stated in the beliefs, clear in what it indicates
It is clear to him in ethics in transactions in
What is clear in the beliefs of God in worship?
We want from the servant what is the other article
اخبارها ايه بعد الموت هيحصل ايه كل شيء
Clear, no ambiguity
There is no clear book in it
عشان كده كلمه مبين دي استدل بها اهل
The Sunnah is that the origin of the book is that it runs
Words are taken literally
This is a great rule.
In it, in the chapter of names and attributes, when our Lord
He says about himself that he has a hand or two hands or he has
A face or he has such and such qualities, so our Lord said
The Book is a clear Book.
The clear book is not clear if it is
There is always ambiguity in the words.
The basic principle is that words are interpreted in their apparent meaning.
لان ده من من البيان ليه ربنا يحدثنا
In riddles, he says the hand, but he does not mean the hand, and he says
The eye, not the eye, but the face
He means the face and we sit and give her everything
We say that it is not what is meant by its appearance, it is not what is meant by its appearance
It is not intended to be apparent without evidence, so how can it be?
The Qur’an is a clear book if all the attributes are not
مراده على ظاهرها فلا يحب ولا يغضب ولا
He laughs, he doesn't come down, he doesn't come back, he has no hand and he doesn't...
He has a face if God speaks to us in riddles
This contradicts the fact that it is a book that explains the Book.
The clear meaning is that when an Arab man hears
He understands the word immediately, no explanation is needed.
The Arab man listens and your Lord came, what will he understand? He came
Your Lord came completely when he heard a
بل يداه مبسوطتان هيفهم ايه؟ يداه مالهاش
معنى عنده المعنى الظاهر كده اذا كان
The whole thing was a metaphor and riddles, it wasn't a book
Explaining that the original meaning of words is to be interpreted in accordance with their context.
It seems that unless evidence comes to indicate that
المعنى الظاهر غير مراد طالما ما فيش دليل
The principle remains that I deal with the apparent meaning
These are the verses of the clear Book.
Indeed, We have sent it down as an Arabic Qur’an that you might understand.
We have sent it down as an Arabic Qur’an. Indeed, We have sent it down. Take now.
حته برض في العقيده احنا بص عايزين نطلع
من الصوره دي بكل حاجه يعني كل احلامك
We achieve this beautiful Surah. We have revealed it.
Our Quran is Arabic, Arabic, oh my God, our Quran is Arabic
طب انزلناه دي ان طب ليه ربنا بيقول ان مش
انا اه دي برض حاجه بتلخبط الناس ان ربنا
Sometimes he expresses himself in the plural and sometimes he expresses himself in the singular.
About himself individually
There is no contradiction when God expresses himself
In individuals, he wants to explain monotheism, and when he expresses
Himself in the plural wants to show greatness because the expression
About the individual as a whole is from glorification as what
I say peace be upon you, not upon you, this is a kind of
Appreciation for what I say to you is your happiness, not your happiness
This is a kind of appreciation when I tell you that we decided
Alaa Hamed, what do I want to do to pamper myself?
God sometimes talks about himself
Individually, as our master Moses said in a position
Monotheism is that I am I, I am God, there is no god but Me
Worship me, but sometimes he talks about himself in the plural.
To show His greatness, He says, “Indeed, it is We who sent down the Qur’an.”
And we will surely protect him. It does not mean that he is talking.
In the plural, it is more than one, but one
He talks about himself in the plural to show the amount
And the glorification is that
Anzalnah
We sent it down. We sent it down as evidence for the Sunnis.
God is above him and God is Most High in the highest and
In His essence, glory be to Him, above His throne, above His heavens
وانه في العلو سبحانه وتعالى تمام خلافا
For the people of innovation, otherwise if he was not in the upper class then why?
He says, “We sent it down.” So the sending down of the Book indicates its superiority.
God is above His creation and He is distinct from His creation and He is in
Glory be to God Almighty, the Most Gracious, as He said:
العرش ايه استوى والادله كتير بقى اليه
The good word ascends, the Book is revealed from God
Dear All-Wise, the angels’ ascension is complete.
Glorify the name of your Lord, the Most High. You who are in the heaven have believed.
That the earth may swallow you up, the subject is long, but this is it.
One of the Sunnis’ proofs of God’s supremacy is me.
We have sent it down as an Arabic Qur’an that you might understand.
Perhaps you will understand.
If the Qur’an is a call to use the mind
Call for the appreciation of reason
An invitation to use the mind in its right place because
The Quran is actually full of rational evidence.
Rational evidence for monotheism
Rational evidence for resurrection
The message, as we saw, is a thousand words to the mother.
My mind is on the Quran, proof of the message
I have lived among you a lifetime before that. Will you not reason?
Correct evidence of resurrection
For example, He is the One who sends the winds as good tidings before the heavens.
His mercy until, when it has carried heavy clouds, We drive them.
To a dead land, so We sent down water into it and brought forth thereby from it
All fruits also occupy your mind as well we go out
The dead, so that you may remember completely, is evidence of monotheism.
Is he who worries like he who does not create? Will you not be reminded?
So you will find a lot of calls to use the mind in
Meditation on contemplation on reflection on contemplation
But unfortunately, some people continue to use their minds in the opposite way.
He is required to use reason in judging.
النصوص فيقول لك النص ده مش جاي معايا
We keep giving it to him, we keep denying it, we keep doubling it, it is not him
It is not the role of the mind, the mind. Yes, first we will see if
The Quran is the Quran, no one is looking for anything else
If the Quran is a Sunnah, we will occupy the mind with knowledge.
The correct and the weak after what remained we knew that this
Quran or we know this is an acceptable hadith that will last forever
There is no choice but to accept it, accept it, accept the judgment
اقبل العقيده واصدقها واعمل بالايه بالحكم
It is not that I will say after that I will enter my mind and say
اصل العقيده دي مش جايه في العقل لا اصل
دي مش مقنعه فناولها فنشيلها فنغيرها يبقى
We are here, the mind, because the mind is the original
I should have known that God is capable of everything.
There is no such thing as telling me something is wrong
العقيده مش موافقه للعقل انا مش بقيس على
My ability is measured by God's ability and God is measured by
All things are possible
My mind tells me that God is wise, so I am not
I will put my mind to the judgments and say I like it and not
عاجبني ده جاي من عند الحكيم انت فاهم مش
فاهم دي مشكلتك الشخصيه فالعقل ده مش
His place is to pass judgments after they have been proven.
Or accept the beliefs or reject them after they have been proven, but
A call to use reason to prove that the text is a text
Then, it is fixed in contemplating and meditating on the text.
And being influenced by it, acting upon it, and deriving rulings
Indeed, We have sent it down as an Arabic Qur’an that you might understand.
Then God Almighty said:
We are back again, we are for glorification, we are for deficiency
To you is the best of stories, in what We have revealed to you.
The Quran, and before that you were among the unaware.
We tell you the best stories. Okay, let's talk.
On two levels, the stories in general are like the Qur’an in general.
The stories of the Quran are the best stories, especially Surat
Joseph or the story of Joseph is the best story in the Quran
Of course, it is fine, and there are reasons for that. We will tell you about them.
Now, but let's talk about the first...
General and then private general
Why are the stories of the Qur’an the best stories in general?
Why is it better than any other stories, whether stories of people?
The distorted book, of course, or the stories of people completely
او اي قصص خلاف القصص اللي جايه مع الوحي
Let's compare them in some things first.
We find the first difference in the stories of the Qur’an
It is characterized by
In short
And do not digress into details that do not have
benefit
And human stories
There is a terrible, terrible digression into every detail.
You can find, for example, a story in the Quran in two lines.
If it was turned into a written story or a series, for example.
These two lines will last for 10 episodes, and there will be more talk and discussion.
Roses and digressions meet the Quran completely
About all the details that are not useful at all
اللي احنا عايزينها
لان الغايه مختلفه وليه ليه الفرق الغايه
Different and the purpose of the stories of the Quran is not the purpose of the stories
الناس اللي بيكتبوا قصص عايزين ايه عايزين
يعملوا يعني حبكه دراميه ويشد الناس ويعمل
Attract and work views even if you put details
It is not necessary, but in the Quran you will find the story
Very brief, two or three lines, we will sit and talk about them
ايام وليالي من عظم الكلام اللي فيها
Ignoring details that are not useful
Focus on useful, salutary content that
يعني يخدم القضيه اللي هنتكلم فيها
Number two honesty the difference in honesty God's stories
Stories of the Prophet, may God bless him and grant him peace, are true and correct.
ريب فيه واما قصص الناس فعامته يعني فيه
اكاذيب كتيره جدا جدا وبل ممكن يكون اصل
The story is a lie, meaning sometimes the story is true
It's all a lie, that's the whole story, or we won't say it's a lie
او متالفه يعني تمام واحيانا بيكون اصل
The story is true, but you will not find it in any real detail.
It just happens for the sake of the plot, as you can see.
For example, when they made a series about my friend or...
A series about our master Joseph. How many things did they happen?
اصلا بس لازم نعمل كده علشان الحبكه
The drama is perfect, all of God’s stories are true, there is nothing wrong with them
Too much talk, too much, all we got was stories.
People are full of useless details.
Grade three
completely
The third difference is the mark that the stories focused on first.
We find that the stories of God Almighty focused on
What improves a servant’s religion and his worldly life is by focusing on
In the story, you focus strongly on the meanings of monotheism.
Focus on connecting you to the names and attributes we will find in
This story is that your Lord is All-Knowing, All-Wise. Indeed, my Lord is Kind.
Whenever He wants, He connects you with anything, in the name of God always.
It connects you to the afterlife, completely and without reward.
The Hereafter is better for those who believe and fear Allah.
He connects you to good deeds, for he is the one who fears God.
Be patient, for Allah does not waste the reward of the patient.
The benefactors take care of you
By the deeds of the heart with the names and attributes in the abode
The end of the story is ultimately the unification of God.
The afterlife is about deeds
The hearts are in it, in the end, the story is targeting
Your heart and aims to give you lessons, sermons and Sunnahs
There was in their stories a lesson for those of understanding.
It was a fabricated hadith, but the second story is a hadith.
He often slanders and his goal is
Lusts
You will find most of the stories revolve around the verse about sex.
مخدرات القتل دعاره ا مشاكل زوجيه ثم في
النهايه هو انت مش عارف هو عايز يوصل ليه
It is a very, very long tragedy.
In the end, in the end, sometimes it's not in your hands
The moral is that sometimes it turns out the opposite in the end.
The lesson is that you sympathize with evil, for example, or that
Evil won in the end, okay? So yes, I am.
Where is the lesson? Tell me, for example.
I watched the series and your heartfelt actions increased, impossible
Tell me, for example, a movie you saw that made you more attached to it.
In the afterlife, tell me, for example, a song you heard or
A novel from the low novels I read and it got worse
Attachment to God, love for God and monotheism increased in
قلبك مش هيحصل انما بتزداد معلومات كتير
Strong in prostitution, sex, drugs and how
Crimes, north, marital problems and ugliness
Marriage, the sweetness of walking north, and the beautiful divorce
هو ده اللي انت بتطلع بيه
Why does this tell us?
The fourth difference The fourth difference between the stories of the Qur’an
And people's stories, we assume that stories other than God's will end.
نهايه سعيده فرضا رغم ان ده مش بيحصل
It will always end with good triumphing over evil.
النهايه المثاليه اللي ما بقتش موجوده
Now that's fine, come on let's see how we got there
Here and how the Quran leads us to the same result
People's stories
اللي بيحصل الاتي عشان اقول لك على مصيبه
It happens in people's stories, you don't notice it
For example, if we watch a series, let us compare between
Series because the series is a story
What happens in the series?
It happens that we watch 29 episodes, 29 episodes.
Drug Crimes Details Details in the murder in
Adultery in marital infidelity in corruption
In evil in prisons, okay, and then the last episode
البطل بيخلص الموضوع في اخر حلقه بيضرب ده
ويعمل دوت ويجيب حقه والتاني ده اتسجن وده
قتل نفسه وبتاع فنفرح ه وبتاع واتاثرنا
Good triumphed over evil, sweet and good
Let's take an example of a real series.
Legend of Mohamed Ramadan
One of his most famous series, I mean it was in...
A huge amount of corruption, and in the end, there is actually good.
It spread on the street theoretically means
In the last episode, "Good guys" after the series "Mohamed"
What happened during Ramadan? They went out with their haircuts.
His and his cattle
بالالفاظ اللي قالها بالصياعه اللي حصلت
In the whole series, and no one is appearing in the series
Why did he repent because of the last episode?
اقول لك بقى ليه عشان دي هتنقلني لروعه
The Quran, because people are affected by what...
He is exposed to it more, even if the mistake is the other person's
He is more affected by what he is exposed to, even if it is a mistake.
If I watch 29 episodes of evil and one episode of good, I
I will come out with evil, not with good
Understood
لو انا بتفرج على 29 حلقه مخدرات ودعاره
وخيانات زوجيه وبتاع وك اخر حلقه الخير
I won individually, I will prove that I have memorized
I wanted to do betrayals and I saved the drugs
I want to drink it and I memorized the words and I want to say them
وده اللي بيحصل الناس بتطلع مسلسلات
With jokes, north, ring, and chains
No one knows if he has repented or not.
عشان اخر حلقه دي جبله في الانسان جبله في
This human being will lead us to the path of the Qur’an.
The beauty of ignoring the details of evil
Focus on the details of goodness
Come on
I will give you an example
Surah or story of Moses, peace be upon him
How was it mentioned in Surat Al-Qasas? What did God say?
He said
We recite to you, in truth, from the news of Moses and Pharaoh.
People who believe
The evil will be explained now. The evil episodes will be explained now.
Now it will be said that Pharaoh was on earth and made
Its people are sects, one group is weakened and the other is slaughtered.
Their sons and their women are kept ashamed. Indeed, he was of
Spoilers, this verse will be deleted if it is made into a series
You will take the 29th episode, 29 episodes, details, he was
بيقتلهم ازاي والنسوان كان بياخدهم ازاي
How does he torture them?
ويغتصبهم ازاي ونقعد بقى 600 حلقه في مشهد
rape
But the Quran has eliminated all evil in the world. Come on.
I have more to do, one by one
And We desired to bestow favor upon those who were oppressed in the land.
And We make them leaders and make them inheritors and establish them
On the earth, and We showed Pharaoh and Haman and their soldiers.
They were not warned, and We revealed to the mother of Moses.
A very terrible digression into the details of the terrible good
All the good details remained another example in the story
Joseph, peace be upon him, and she desired him and he desired her
ده مشهد الشر وبعد كده الخير لولا ان راى
Proof of his Lord. Thus do We turn away from him the indecent question.
انه من عبادنا المخلصين المشهد ده لو
It will be made into a two-episode series. Here are the details.
عملت ازاي ولبست ايه وبصت له وبص مشكله
Stay
ده الفرق
ده الفرق من الفراقات ايضا عشان كده انا
What do you get from the Quran? I get it with goodness.
بالمشاهد الخير الكتير قوي اللي انا شفتها
One of the differences is the ultimate goal.
The goals of the story The goal of the stories of the Qur’an is the heart
The righteousness of a person is the righteousness of his religion, the righteousness of his worldly life, and his relationship
By God, his relationship with the afterlife is the ultimate story.
Earthly desires and sights
Regardless, there are no values ​​or constants left.
انما اللي بيجي يجيب مشاهدات هو ده اللي
In the past, for example, it was normal for movies to...
اللي بتجيب مشاهدات لما الخير ينتصر على
الشر دلوقتي مابقاش كده خلي بالك دلوقتي
People tend to think that evil is better in the end and I sympathize.
معاه يعني هو دي المسلسلثات بتاخذ كده
The issue is based on air, there are no rules
There are no values, there are no constants, so I can
I will take you and bring you back as I want
والفرق اللي بعد كده هو في الاثر في
النهايه انت شفت افلام كتير ومسلسلات كتير
و وحكاوي وقريت قصص كتير قو لي الاثر اللي
You have changed your relationship with God.
The afterlife, the righteousness of your heart, and the righteousness of your religion
And your acceptance of worship and tell me the effect of Surah
One of the Quran in the same direction in Salah
Your heart, your religion, your relationship with God, and your acceptance of
العباده هتعرف ساعتها ان في فرق كبير وان
We tell you the best stories
I hope you understood something
Ok, let's go into the story of Joseph, peace be upon him.
Especially because the story of Joseph is the best story in
The best stories, I mean the story of Joseph, is the best story in
The Qur’an, without a doubt, contains all its details.
Very big, complete story from beginning to end
The details are perfect and of course it is a very touching story.
بكل المعايير عشان كده البعض يقول لك ايه
يعني البعض ليه تاملات في كلمه احسن ليه
Why is the story of Joseph, peace be upon him, the best story?
هقول لكم كده كم حاجه يعني
مش مش هشرحها يعني بس هقولها لكم من على
A way to mention some of the niceties
Some of them said that it is the best story because it included
Envious and envied
And the lover and the beloved, the owner and the owned, the witness and the witnessed.
And Habis
And imprisoned
And fertility, and sorrow, and joy, and poverty, and wealth, and sleep.
And his vigilance
حلوه مش هقولها تاني عشان اقول لكم واحده
Another one, and some said that it is the best story.
Because it included love, envy and separation
And the meeting, patience, and regret
And forgiveness
Some said it is the best story because it included
On all types of movements from one situation to another
From hardship to blessing, from humiliation to glory, and from slavery to slavery
To the king and from his division and dispersion to the meeting
And harmony, from sadness to happiness, and from drought to
Prosperity and from hardship to spaciousness, it is beautiful. By God, I liked it.
يعني في حاجات كده بتوقفني
I want to tell you, that is, by what we have revealed to you.
The Quran God is greater, and you were before it to whomever
The heedless, even though you were before that among the heedless.
يعني ايه الغافلين ليه ربنا وصف النبي
May God’s prayers and peace be upon him, if he was one of them
The heedless were described in Surah, and he said, “He found you lost.”
فهدى يعني ايه من الغافل يعني ايه كان ضال
May God’s prayers and peace be upon him
Heedless
That is, God explained it at the end of Surat Ash-Shura, saying:
And thus We have inspired in you a spirit of Our command to complete what you have been given.
You did not know what the Book and faith were.
Do you know what the book and faith mean? I was not
You know the details, I mean the Prophet, peace be upon him
Peace be upon you
Word
Negligent means you do not know. Negligent means you do not know.
وصلتلكش المعلومه فده مش مش حاجه عيب فيه
Meaning, what did you not reach? The word “lost” is the word “lost.”
It has two meanings: a stray is one who does not know the truth.
He tells you to get lost
And the one who turns away from the truth has strayed. So when our Lord describes the Prophet
If he was astray, he would still mean the first meaning.
He who does not know the truth is not exempt from it
The truth is that the Prophet, may God bless him and grant him peace, was not there.
He was completely ignorant of the truth, but he knew some of the truth.
As evidence that he, peace and blessings be upon him, was in
Ignorance until he was on monotheism on his way
Abraham, peace be upon him, did not prostrate
For an idol that did not drink wine, did not listen to music, was not
بيذني ما كانش بيعمل افعال الجاهليه فكان
He knows in general what remains of the religion of Abraham some
The verse has some limited details.
But he didn't have the rest of the details.
Other house details
Details of the rituals, how do I fast, and what is it?
ايه اللي هيحصل بعد الموت ايه لسه
التفاصيل مش عنده هي دي معنى غافل ما كان
He knows the details, even if it was just generalities.
He knew it and was committed to it, so he was on monotheism
He had good morals in general.
He generally avoided all evils.
He did not do anything forbidden in the pre-Islamic era, but what?
He knows the details, but he doesn't know about purification and dry ablution.
والغسل يعني في حاجات لسه ما نعرفهاش
I don't know the details of the beliefs in faith in God
The Last Day and the angels in the details
I don't know her
This is the meaning
The heedless or the meaning of the one who is astray in his right, peace be upon him
Peace be upon you
But he was generally on monotheism and was
In general, it is about righteousness, but the details of monotheism
The details of the rectitude did not reach us.
ثم انتقل بقى بدا بنا الايه جمال مال كله
When Joseph said to his father, "God is great," he immediately entered.
We built the Surah in the goal when Joseph said to his father
Oh my father, I saw ten stars, the sun
And the moon saw them prostrating to me. He said, O my son, no.
Tell your brothers about your dream and they will plot against you.
Satan is a clear enemy to man. Good, we have moved on.
You will notice that the Surah
ا ذكرت الاول مشهد مشهد واحد بس مشهد واحد
بس في علاقه يوسف عليه السلام بيعقوب عليه
Peace then began a second beginning from the beginning of his saying
There were in Joseph and his brothers signs for the inquirers.
خد بالك يعني الاول حصل مشهد كده لمستقل
Completely about the story and then we started the story from
The first remained, there were signs in Joseph and his brothers
For those asking, when he said, when he said, what is this scene?
I will explain this scene to you now. You will discover the scene.
This is the story column.
The story column and the whole story are built on the scene
ده عشان كده ربنا ذكره لوحده وهو باختصار
How did Jacob raise Joseph, peace be upon him?
how
Jacob made Joseph, peace be upon him
For the sake of dignity
He works, raises, establishes or maintains assets.
What is the connection between Joseph, peace be upon him, and the verse?
للعظمه اللي احنا بنشوفها منه عليه
peace.
Firstly
We notice in the story
Joseph, peace be upon him
I had a dream.
The first person he thought of telling him was his father.
This is something very striking. How?
الواحد لما بيفكر في حاله كده او حال اغلب
Young people or most people, me and I, if I saw
I dreamed that I went to tell my father
You tell me it's hard
I don't mean to say "no" to my parents, my parents don't even laugh.
مني ومش هيقعد يتكلم معايا و ممكن يسخر
مني وممكن يقوللي بقوللك انا مش مش رايق
You still need to tell me about your dreams
Also, I can't stand you when I'm awake
You still have dreams to tell me
So if that means that, then you will tell the dream
ليه؟ تقول لي اللي يعني اللي بيحبني اللي
اللي هيستحملني اللي هيقبلني واللي
هيصدقني واللي مش هيسخر مني ولا هياخد
Seriously
If Jacob, peace be upon him, had these qualities
And Joseph, peace be upon him, dealt with him on
انه فيه الصفات ديت اذا ما كانش والد اللي
هو اوامر ونواهي و وصرامه وبيتعامل كده
Army and Baba, Baba is not affectionate, Baba is not
بيسمعناش بابا ما بيقعدش معانا ما فيش
Dot talk
This is Jacob, peace be upon him, extending his hand to Joseph, peace be upon him.
Peace is a lot of reassurance, security, love and respect
Appreciate, understand, and contain
Let Joseph, peace be upon him
لما شاف منام اول حد فكر يقول له ابوه
father
You can't imagine what it means to be the first one to think of
فيه ابويا يبقى ابويا ده احلى من صاحبي
احسن من صاحبي تمام مش ده انت ممكن تقول
Don't tell your friend, or your father, or I will tell you
I don't tell my father to be my friend, my father is closer to me
From my friend, and this is just the beginning.
The normal personality of Joseph, peace be upon him, is a normal father
Understand his educational role
بيدي كل مشاعره وحنانه وقلبه واحتوائه
And his affection for the son
مش بيتعامل ميري مش بيتعامل اوامر مش
He acts like he is in the army
We notice here that they are both sitting alone.
True, as evidenced by the fact that no one has heard of the dream.
He told him not to confine his vision to his brothers, even though
How many children does the father have? 11, not including Youssef.
Peace be upon him
He has energy and the capacity to sit with everyone.
واحد لوحده الواحد لو عنده 12 عيل ده مش
I tell you, I tell you what, you mean, he meets them
He will meet them for lunch, but he will meet them in...
He will meet them at the meeting on the trip.
عنديش خلق بقى اقعد مع كل واحد لوحده ده
انا 12 واحد لا ده يعقوب عليه السلام عنده
Ready to sit with each one alone
ويسمعه ويقعد يحكي معاه حكايه طويله قوي
And be patient with him and give him sermons and advice and solve it for him
His words and understanding of right and wrong, that's you
عارفين ان هو ده اللي احنا مفتقدينه في
Our homes
We miss the private session in our homes
Between mother and daughter and son, between father and son
And the daughter's private session
Most of us think that he is fine if I am fine
In general, of course, there are bad role models.
We will not talk about bad models, but I
He says that even the good examples among us, he remembers
نفسه كويس بس لما تيجي تقارن نفسك بيعقوب
Peace be upon him
Not yet
الام فعلا الكويسه هي اللي بتقعد مع تقفل
The door is closed on her and her daughter and they sit down
They chat for an hour and she tells him the details of what happened.
At school, she told me and did for me, and she is the mother
Picking up
عشان تربي تقول لها خد بالك من دي لا ديت
No, this is better. No, this is not how you should react here.
It would stay like this and you would get reactions from her.
So you can get to know her personality more and raise her
The best father is the one who sits with his son and tells him to tell me
حصل ايه والابن نفسه بيجي يقعد مع بابا
بامان بابا مش مش هيزعقني مش هيضربني مش
هيهزقني مش هيسخر مني مش هيتنمر عليا مش
He is less than me
بيحبني فبقعد احكي له حصل ايه في النادي
What happened at the gym and what happened with my friends?
وبابا بيحبني قوي بيتلطف معايا بيش بيشكر
فيا الحاجه الحلوه اللي بعملها في في نفس
If time warns me of something, I benefit from it.
قوي من ابويا انا بحب احكي له عشان دايما
In my back and my strong friend, my father, the private council
Not this year
مع كل واحد لوحده عشان اقرا كل واحد لوحده
اللي بيعمل كده ده اللي بيربي صح ما
بنعملش كده يبقى لسه في لسه قدامنا شويه
Until we reach the right model in education
The private council was repeated many times, we saw it in every
Prophets and righteous people
A private council between Abraham, peace be upon him
واسماعيل عليه السلام وهو بيقول يا بني
The same words are: I see in my dream that I
I will slaughter you and see what you see
He said, "O my father, do as you are commanded. You will find me, God willing."
God is among the patient
Private council between
Luqman and his son say, "My son."
It is as little as a mustard seed, my son.
Establish prayer, enjoin what is right, and refrain from what is wrong.
Friendly base
القاعده اللطيفه اللي مش جيش مش اوامر مش
Mary is a love base full of containment, love, femininity and beauty
Kindness between father and son
Then one of the attributes is
The session is a matter of sophistication in dealing.
الرقي بقى اللي هو ايه خيالي
The son says my father, my son
And the father replied to him, saying, “My son, my son, what is it?”
They said, "Oh boy, oh girl, you are my beloved."
Okay, son
الابن مش هيقول يا ابتي غير لما يسمع من
His father says, "My son."
Don't ask your son to respect you while you are belittling him.
Going and coming
Don't ask your son to treat you with respect
I curse him with the dirtiest words
At least the mistake of Ibn Toul Nahar is being told.
A dog or an animal, and a girl is called a boot or a...
غبيه يا حماره وبعد كده الابن تيجي يكلم
His father tells him that he has to stop while talking to him.
You respect your father, kiss my hand and my head and say
Oh, my God, my father.
Where are you? You're a mess.
The son is the father's mirror, the daughter is the mother's mirror
When she sees her mother, she says sorry, meaning she is rude
She has a long tongue, swears, backbites and slanders.
And the wind
كانت بتت لو طلعت شبه امها
انت اللي عملت فيه كده ما تطلبيش منها
Look, she is affectionate, kind-hearted, and treats her husband well.
كويس ما انت كنت بتعاملي ابوها مش كويس هي
She left her mother's house and was bad with her father
She did this to her husband, and now her mother is trying to...
Fix what's between them, laugh at who she is
Mirror for you
I want my son to be something, so I should do it first.
My son is a blank slate, when he finds the house he will respect it
Some of them respect my wife and talk to her in the most beautiful way.
I say the most beautiful words to her
She sees my middle daughter, for example, she sees me talking
How do I talk to my older sister respectfully and politely?
And caress her and kiss her
هتطلع عامله ازاي هي ما شافتش غير كده فهي
ما تعرفش ان في قله ادب يعني يعني ممكن لو
She went to another house and saw the father cursing his son
والابن بيشوح لابوه تقول ايه الناس
الغريبه دي رغم ان ده ممكن نموذج العادي
But she didn't see it like that. She doesn't know anyone but him.
Why you, why you guys? Aren't you?
بتحترموا ابائكم ليه؟ هو الاب مش بيحترم
ولاده ليه؟ هي ما تعرفش الكلام دوت
فلن تجد بيتقال فيها ابتي الا البيت اللي
It is said, my son
Note here
These
يوسف عليه السلام بيحكي فعلا حاجه غريبه
It's really strange if my father is not Jacob
Peace be upon him, he took the matter with sarcasm
He could have said an unnecessary word to his son.
وهو بيقول له كده لو بيقول له بقول لك ايه
You sit and see me as planets and suns and I tell you
Oh man, go to sleep, you'll hurt me
Why is my brain missing you? What should I tell you?
I am not dead, that's it, but what about you?
Amal disappointed me, if I talked to you it would only be in my dreams
And my ambitions and you break me I tell you, Dad
I wish he would keep telling me, "Son, you will always fail."
You, my son, you have no need for it, and the girl says
لي بابا نفسي اعمل وبتاع يا بنت تلهي على
You stay home and go to the kitchen
How do you want your son to be a human being?
As soon as he tells you a story or tells you about a dream
His dreams or he tells you one of his goals and he sticks to it
If you shake him, he won't tell you again and you won't know who he is.
بيعمل ايه بعد كده وهيكبر وهتبقى انت مش
عارف هو فين وخرج فين وج منين وبيشتغل ايه
وبي الفلوس دي جايبها منين ولا هيقول لك
خلاص كان زمان كان من زمان انت ما اديتنيش
I'm safe talking to you anyway
You didn't contain me, you were supposed to appreciate what I said
Even if I say something stupid, I'm sorry if I say something stupid
You could understand what I was saying. I was too young to understand.
I'm sorry, I have to
when
I appreciate my son's words, I appreciate them on his level, not his
My level is that I'm sorry, but my daughter can come
You're telling me really pointless things.
As for me, I can turn it into a joke, but it's coming
She tells me that she is nervous and angry, and I feel that
هي واخده الموضوع بجديه ومحموقه وحصل كده
وعملت لي كده وبتاع
You have to deal with the level of speech at the level of
Her understanding is not at the level of your understanding because she sees
The topic is big and I think it is very important
Don't you think it's a trivial matter? It really is trivial.
For you and for me, but he is not
It was insignificant to him
فلو انت قلت لها ان الموضوع ده تافه هي مش
Come tell me again
You will know when your children do not come to talk
You need to know that you
I did not give them security
I couldn't stand their words, so I called them several times and they hung up.
I told you some stupid things several times
It happened to me, sorry, I mean it happens to them in schools
كان المفروض رد فعلك ان انت طب ايه اللي
It happened, tell me, how did this happen? No, no, no.
ما ينفعش ابدا وانت عملتي ايه وتعالي
Give me a hug, my love. I mean I appreciate it.
قوي الموقف اللي انت اخدتيه وانت صبرتي
كتير واستحملتي كتير مع ان اصلا يعني هوا
But I speak with his mind, not mine
Your son will come and tell you everything then. He is my father.
ده لما بحكيله بيقدرني بيرفعني فوق و فعلا
He respects my words, he will involuntarily find himself
He wants to tell you
Sorry, if your son had the same dream
Joseph, peace be upon him, if you do not know the story of Joseph
Peace be upon him, you will mock him and say:
Name of the person
دي مشكله احنا مش عارفين نتعامل مع
Our children, yes, containment. It is true that I contain them.
Get down to his level, but that's the bottom line. Get down to his level.
His ideas and deal with the importance of the subject according to
Its importance to him is not its importance to me
انا وادي له وقت ما استخسرش فيه وقت ده
اغلى حاجه عنديش انا مش فاضي انجز في
Speak up, my son. I don't have time for you. Don't talk.
ابني خد راحتك اقعد بقى سيب بقى اللي في
ايدك نقعد ايه اللي حصل واقعد معاه نص
He talks to me for an hour and I talk to him, raise him and advise him
I will give him my experience. That's it, my son. I'm full.
بابا كفايه كده طب اتوكل على الله لو في
Another thing, come to me, my heart is open
You have time, my son. Whenever you come, I will come.
صاحبك يعني تخيل ابن ابوه بيعامله كده مش
هيحتاج بقى يضربه مش هيحتاج يهزقه مش
He needs to tell him, "My son, don't listen to me. Listen to me."
My son, if his father told him anything
He would have done it to your friend if his mother had told him anything.
حاجه هيعملها حب بقى يعني اشتغلوا على
Love, guys
Work on love a little
Joseph, peace be upon him, speaks reassuringly in
A serious topic, of course. He told him that he saw someone
The planets, the sun, and the moon, I showed them prostrating to me.
The religion here is Jacob, peace be upon him, remained a sense
The topic is very, very, very big
First, he understands the vision all the time.
The vision means the most dangerous thing possible.
What can
And he translated it
It is known that the 11 planets are sisters of the sun.
The moon, father and mother
بيسجدوا له يعني طبعا السجود هنا سجود
Honoring the angels' prostration to Adam is not prostration
عباده ماينفعش حد يسجد لحد عباده لكن في
The law before us was beneficial to someone who wanted to be honored.
One means to appreciate him or express his respect for him
يسجد له لكن في دنا اتلغى الموضوع ده
The Prophet, peace and blessings be upon him, said: If it were
This topic remained. I ordered the woman to prostrate.
لزوجها تقدير واحترام عشان حقه لكن خلاص
مافيش حتى السجود التكريم ده اتلغى عندنا
All
In Joseph, peace be upon him
B is of course he saw and realized the seriousness of the situation
The sun and the moon are very big, of course there is a difference in
The sun and the moon, who is the sun and who is the moon?
So say it, by the way, there are people
They said that the sun is the mother and the moon is the father
And people said that the sun is not the father and the moon is not the father
She is the mother, it is a matter of controversy, even if I am
It means
I feel inclined like this because the father is the sun
Mother is the moon
Why? First, it started with the sun.
والقمر فعاده الاب اللي بيقدم.
Where is the sun shining?
And heat.
The moon is just shining
والاب هو اللي بيبقى فيه اضاءه وحراره لان
The father has the light, meaning he has it.
المشاعر والتربيه وكل حاجه وفي الحزم
والشده اللي هي الحراره
في عنده سلاح ثاني والام عاده بيغلب عليها
Lighting, but kindness, mercy and severity
فيها بتبقى اقل شويه
So, the interpretation of the sun as the father is closer to a meeting.
Lighting with heat and the interpretation of the mother with the moon
It is closer to being less lit and warm or what
Fish heat
Another benefit if we say that the sun is the father
The moon's light is always a reflection of the sun, right?
Also the father is the pillar of the house
لو نور البيت كله ينور والام تنور تمام
The father really, really, really can make it.
Mother makes the house happy and can ruin it
All of them, meaning the more enlightened the father was.
The mother is more enlightened and the mother's response remains a reaction
So, guys, we remember the responsibility of the father. The father is important.
Very much so
He said, “By the sun and the moon, you saw them prostrating to me first.”
need
The first prevention of corruption
Preventing corruption He said, O my son, do not tell your dream to
Your brothers, you are sure that Satan is plotting against man.
A clear enemy
Let's first talk about vision and its types.
بسرعه كل رؤيه ممكن اعمل معاها ايه الرؤيه
On three types or what a person sees in
Dreams are of three types
The first type
هي رؤيه الحق اللي هي من الله وعاده دي
بتكون رؤيه واضحه جدا تفاصيلها واضحه
ومنطقيه تمام وبيبقى فيها سكينه وطمانينه
Fadi, this is a true vision. If it is really a vision from God
I think I saw something good or something
حاجه شر
لو شفت حاجه خير اعمل ايه النبي عليه
Peace and blessings be upon him. He said: If one of you sees what he likes
Only those who love him should tell it, just like our master Jacob.
He says to Joseph, peace be upon him
If one of you sees something he likes, he should not tell anyone about it except those he loves.
loves
Because of envy, if one of you sees something he dislikes
He said: No one should be buried in it. No one should be buried in it.
Never, you neither love him nor do you like him. Forget that you
شفتها ده الحل واوصى عليه الصلاه والسلام
اللي شاف حاجه بيكرهها كذا وصيه قال لا
Someone tells him to turn to the other side.
If I am still in bed, I will change my clothes and sleep on them
My other side said: And let him who seeks refuge seek refuge in God
I seek refuge in Allah from the evil of this.
The vision is moving to his left three
No one talks about it or asks for its interpretation ever.
Because one of the reasons for getting
The vision has its interpretation. If it is interpreted, it will happen.
فطالما اي حاجه انت مش عاجبها مش حاببها
Don't ask about its interpretation. Some people ask about it.
اي منام بيشوفه منام مش حلو ما تحكوش لحد
I seek refuge in God from his evil. A child on your left three times.
Forget about your sleep, forget about it completely, as if it were you
I saw him
Okay, so the second type of vision remains...
حاجه بتشوفها بس هي من الشيطان
ودي في الغالب بتبقى حاجه مش مفهومه
ملخبطه كده ومحزنه ومالهاش مالهاش ملامح
You don't know how to say it well, but it's annoying
احيانا الثالثه اللي هي بتبقى حديث نفس
يعني واحد عنده امتحان بكره نام حلم
بالامتحان دي مالهاش تفسير واحده بكره
فرحها نامت حلمت بفستان الفرح وبجوزها
مالهاش تفسير واحد عنده عمليه بكره نام
حلم بالدكتور والعمليه مالهاش تفسير لان
This is a conversation that anyone who is busy with something else would have.
What will he find himself doing? What will he find himself thinking about?
لوحده فهمنا طيب عشان كده بقى سيدنا يعقوب
Peace be upon him, he said to him, “Do not tell your dream to anyone.”
Your brothers are plotting against you. There is no benefit here.
The first benefit
It is our master Jacob
He knows his children well
He knows his children very well, which is proof that he cares.
بيهم كلهم خلي بالكم بس طبعا يوسف عليه
السلام هو بيقبل عليه اكتر فاكيد اللي
He is more accepted and gets more attention.
لكن هو مهتم بيهم كلهم مش معنى ان ولاده
مش مش احسن حاجه دلوقتي ان هو مهملهم
هو مهتم بيه ومركز معاهم كلهم وبيديهم
I care about them all, as I know their personalities well.
He told him not to be mean to his sisters, or he would plot against him.
كيدا عارف دماغهم كويس جدا وعارف بيفكروا
في ايه كمان
الحاجه اللي بعد كده نتعلم من يعقوب عليه
Peace be upon you, if I knew that there was an evil person or
He envies me or plots against me, so it is in my best interest
Hide from him
الخير اللي عندي ما استطعت ما في حاجات ما
اعرفش اخفيها في حاجات هي طبيعتها الظهور
But I can hide everything from him of blessings
Hide it as much as possible as much as possible without
I feel sorry for myself, but I don't want to tell him in the first place
من نفسي كده فمن الرحمه بيه لان النفوس مش
Salma, he might be jealous of me
So and so, of course the worst thing is that you publish it
All the good things happen to you on the media because the media
Do not discriminate, reach all people, and share
فضلا عن الناس اللي بتشوفك في كل اتجاه
فانت بيشوفك اللي بيحبك واللي بيكرهك
واللي عايز لك الخير واللي عايز لك الشر
واللي بيحسدك واللي بيدعي لك عشان كده يا
One of the stupidest things is that we keep publishing
All our sweet things are on the internet, and I wish we could.
بننشر الوحش معاها عشان نقول للناس احنا
عندنا وحش برده لا ننشر حلو بس فطبعا
The second one is that you don't live in a kingdom
Nothing bad is happening to you, so come on now
You have three eyes, come on, lie down in bed now
Don't post anything, guys. I want to tell you.
Tell your loved one what you will tell him on the media
هتوصل اللي بتحبه بس هتوصل بكوكب كله يبقى
الكلام ده يتقال كده بيني وبينك فيس تو
Vest in front of you, not on the media
He told him
He is plotting against you
وبعد كده عشان يوسف عليه السلام ما يكرهش
What are his sisters, considering that his sisters are
بشر والبشر حتى لو كان مش صالح دلوقتي قد
He is getting better
He may get better
The bad person is a victim of a devil who seduced him.
He is also guilty, but our master Jacob transferred him to
The enmity of Satan himself remained, they transferred it to a higher transfer
As if he wanted to tell him that they are your sisters and not them
Your real enemies because they might be tomorrow
They changed, your real enemy, my son, is
The devil wants you to focus on your enemy, focus on him
The devil, because tomorrow God may guide your sisters
وهو حس المعنى ده من الرؤيه ما هم هيسجدوا
For Youssef, how if they envy him, then of course as long as
If they prostrate to him, then they are satisfied with him, then he will be reconciled.
Their condition is such that he does not want to create enemies among them.
His sisters and he says to him, your sisters are a monster, where is that?
Mothers fall between their children
ده في عيله بيوقعوا بين بعض ده يعقوب عليه
Peace be upon you, Lord of my son, may your heart remain perfect with you.
Your sisters, your problem is with the devil.
للانسان عدو مبين عشان كده كان سهل على
Youssef forgives his sisters and in the end he said no leaks
Today my problem is that I was not with you
زمان ويوسف عليه السلام عبر عن الموضوع ده
At the end of the story, when he said after he had been tempted
The devil is between me and my brothers. My Lord is kind to me.
يشاء سبحان الله تربيه عجيبه فاذا اول
Something that Jacob connected to Joseph, peace be upon him
Satan's enmity
ودي خلاصه التربيه اللي جايه بقى هو اصلا
There are only two things: the enmity of Satan and the love of the Most Merciful.
يوسف عليه السلام كل الابداع اللي عمله في
The story is a result of these two origins, that he was raised
On the enmity of Satan and the love of the Most Merciful, he led to enmity
The devil is here, come on, the love of the Most Gracious has come
How did he begin to love him for the sake of God in two ways? First:
Mention of livestock
Mentioning the attributes, or we can call it mentioning the benefit
المتعدي اللي هو النفع اللي بيجي لك من
Our Lord and the mention of the attributes of our Lord
Because anyone or anything that loves in the world loves
الحاجتين هم ما فيش غيرهم هم نفس الحاجتين
Countries either for his own qualities or for his qualities
Transgressive
So now he will tell him that God chose you
Transitive adjective: “an” “an” “da na’im” “in’am” is transitive but
I tell him that your Lord is All-Knowing and All-Wise. This is a quality.
Self in God, but anyone who knows that we love anyone
Hakim Beithab, let me give you an example so you will understand now.
اللي جاي وانا هحاول اختصر عشان ما اطولش
You have five more minutes
You now
بتحب الورده ليه تقول لي عشان شكلها حلو
Well, I benefited from something, but it looks nice.
You can like a picture on your mobile phone so I can't smell it
If she looks pretty, she deserves to be loved. What about you?
الشارع عندكم واحد ربنا رزقه ببيبي كده
Beautiful boy
The boy is so beautiful and his cheeks are so red
وبتاع فانت اول ما شفته حبيته ليه عشان
His affairs
His cheeks are puffy and red. Okay, so who are you?
استفدت حاجه كده لا حبيته ليه عشان هو
امور طيب بعد كده الولد دوت كبر وبقى ذكي
It turned out that he is smart, I liked him more, but I benefited
حاجه لا بس هو يتحبى عشان هو ذكي يبقى دي
صفه ذاتيه فيه الولد كبر بعد كده بقى اشطر
One of the most polite people I liked at school
The person who completed the Quran the most, who was most dutiful to his parents
I loved it more, but I haven't benefited from it yet.
He just needs to have good qualities, so he can be loved for that.
صفاته الحلوه طب كبر قوي وبقى صاحب شركه
The oldest and richest man in the area, I loved him more
I have not come across anything until now.
Days passed and I became poor and a man came to me and said to me
Oh man, you have always been a man who loves me. Take it.
He paid my debts and repaid all my debts. It will happen.
ايه بقى اوف المحبه هتضرب فوق قوي لان هنا
He began to move from just not just his personal qualities
There is still a benefit that I get from him. Imagine if it was every day.
Give me the same amount
Okay, imagine if he stood by me a lot
تخيل شغلني او شغل ولادي او او ابنه اتجوز
My daughter, you are our honor
He started to come to me from him, yes, I love him so much, oh, love
رهيب طب ينفع في يوم من الايام اعصيه ده
لو قال لي اي حاجه هعملها اي حاجه حلال مش
ممكن ابدا راجل مش ممكن يا جماعه ده راجل
محترم وبتاع ده لو ما بيعملش معايا حاجه
This is a shroud, I am embarrassed by it, he is a respectable man
ده امال بقى لما قلت لك عمل معايا ايه
ماقدرش اعصي عشان كده هتلاقي سيدنا يوسف
The length of the story is fixed and does not change. He said, God forbid, that
ربي ايه احسن مسواي صح جبل ما وقعش في اي
A sin that loves our Lord, he is strong and calls to God in
Prison, even though he is in prison, he says, “Oh, that’s who”
God's grace upon us and upon people, but more
People do not thank God and call to Him
the prison
ليه عشان يتربي على المحبه طب يعقوب عليه
السلام اصل المحبه دي فين؟ بنفس الفكرتين
Countries that talk about the inherent attributes and qualities of our Lord
Or his benefit to Joseph, peace be upon him, so he remained
So what does he say to him? And thus your Lord chooses you.
Your Lord chooses you, that is, He selects and selects you.
And he knew that this was a choice
And if he is chosen for prophethood, they also said that he will choose you.
Your Lord chooses you and teaches you
They didn't say, my son, I'm the one who taught you. Be careful.
Jacob is a terrible role model, honestly.
They didn't say, "My son, I'm the one who taught you," even though...
هو اللي معلمه فعلا هو المعلم بتاعه هو
His sheikh is his teacher, his mentor. They said to him, “My son.”
You saw my upbringing. What do you think of my upbringing? I raised you.
My son, the flesh of your shoulder is from the goodness of the good father
A good father would not do this to his children.
بالله يقول لهم ربنا اللي بيعلمني
وبيعلمكم ربنا اللي بيعطيني وبيعطيكم
يربط ولاده بالله عشان يحبوا ربنا عشان ما
يعصهوش بعد كده عشان يقدر يسيبهم وهو مطمن
حتى في الخلوات مش هيعصى ربنا لان انا لو
He tied me to him, he will appreciate me while I am here, but I was absent
هيعمل اللي هو عايزه
فهمت حاجه دي مشكله ولادنا قدامنا ملايكه
In front of us are angels saying, “This son is well-mannered, this son is not…”
He would never do that, my dear daughter. Your son is in...
The school is full of children
You say, my son, my son, this is a very strong matter
بيعملش حاجه ما هو قدامك ما بيعملش حاجه
Because you raised him to appreciate you
مش مصدقه انه بيشتم مش مصدقه ان هو بيعمل
عاده سيئه مش مصدقه انه بيشرب
احنا ما ربيناش فيه حب ربنا
Fear of our Lord in the unseen
He says to him, your Lord wants you, your Lord says to him, your Lord does not want you.
قالوش ربنا حتى ربك وكانه بيعمل علاقه
خاصه بين يوسف وبين وبين بين ربنا ويعلمك
God of interpretation
Hadiths
And may His blessings be upon you, and may His blessings be very great.
He tells him that you will reach the fullness of this blessing.
If a person had only 100 blessings, he would have complete hopes.
The blessing is fulfilled because he realized that he would attain prophethood.
Because this is the highest blessing. There are degrees of blessings.
For example, I, Alaa, am a Muslim. It is a blessing that I am.
A converted Muslim is a great blessing that I am
It is a great blessing to be among God’s saints.
قوي قوي اوصل للنبوه طبعا ما فيش حد بيوصل
النبوه خلاص ان واحد يوصل للنبوه ده اعلى
Something left and may His blessings be upon you and upon the family of Jacob
كان بيقول له انت النعمه مش عليك انت بس
This is a blessing for you, your father, your grandfather and
Your grandfather
Perfect, and upon the family of Jacob, as he completed it, he completed it upon
Your parents before him were Abraham and Isaac
It's like all the blessings, guys. What a blessing for the father.
A blessing for the son is a blessing for the grandfather, a blessing for the grandson.
When my grandfather becomes a good man, I benefit.
When my grandfather was rich, I benefited from what I heard from my grandfather.
It's nice that I benefited, because every blessing from the father is a blessing
Every blessing is upon the son, every blessing is upon the grandfather
Son, see that God has blessed you with many blessings
May God bless you and the family of Jacob.
You completed your fathers before you, Abraham and Isaac.
And thus they linked two of the names
Your Lord is All-Knowing and All-Wise. Why did He choose All-Knowing and All-Wise?
very
خليني ارجع الاول لفايده وبعد كده اجي هنا
End
He said to him: And so He will choose you.
Jacob, peace be upon him, understood the Sunnah
Choosing only comes after another trial.
Write it, Jacob, peace be upon him, understood the Sunnah
Choosing only comes after a trial
If God is in conflict, trials will come upon you.
So prepare and welcome it well
And it was said to Imam Al-Shafi’i: Which of the two do you prefer?
Can a man be afflicted? He said: It is not possible until
He is afflicted, he cannot be afflicted until he is afflicted
He understood that there would be trials and that Joseph was against them.
Peace be upon him, he will see very severe trials in his life.
عشان يوصل المنزله ديت
enough
It is possible when trials happen
هيسال يوسف نفسه ليه بيحصل معاه كده فتكون
The answer is that your Lord is All-Knowing and All-Wise.
And another thing, when the affliction happens, it will disappear.
The answer will be that your Lord is wise over him.
He is chosen and selected and leads to prophethood
He might ask his sisters the same question.
اشمعنى انا مش واحداني من اخواتي هي اللي
If I were you, the answer would be the same: Your Lord is All-Knowing.
حكيم بس ودي اجابه بتريحك في حاجات كتيره
very
When our master Noah asked our Lord, he said, “My son is from…”
My family, your promise is true and you are the best of judges
He said, "O Noah, he is not of your family. He has done something unlawful."
Saleh, do not ask me what you do not know.
I advise you not to be among the ignorant
ففي حاجات كتير قوي ما عندناش بيها علم بس
This answer is enough for us, your Lord is All-Knowing and All-Wise.
In Joseph, peace be upon him, he was raised with a strong upbringing.
عداوه الشيطان محبه الرحمن دي اللي صنعت
Joseph, peace be upon him, wanted to know this craft.
When did it appear? Why did it appear in every scene?
He was in prison and he made the prisoners love God
رغم ان هو في السجن ممكن يقول ده ربنا
اللي عمل فيا كده وبتاع ما شافش كده شاف
Your Lord is All-Knowing, All-Wise, and He sees that this is good, God willing.
God is our Lord, and He says that this is from the grace of God.
On us and on the people and the masters of the dispersed say
Is it better for God, the One, the Almighty, to resist his desire?
النساء اللي هي محبوبه لاي راجل بحبه لله
God forbid that my Lord is better than me. He said, “Lord of prison.”
I love what they invite me to. Come to me and stay in
The end of the story and see the terrible effect of raising Jacob
Ali Youssef, although the meeting that took place between
Jacob Jacob Joseph in the end it was after 40 years
He said, "My father, look, this is an interpretation of upbringing."
My dream ten years ago, 40 years later, for the first time
He has been a member of the council for 40 years, but not now.
ناسي ولا كلمه من اللي حصلت في القاعده
الوديه دي عشان بقول لك المجلس الخاص مع
اولادنا هو ده اللي بيثبت لكن الكلام
The year is forgotten
He said this is the interpretation of a vision from before that he made it clear.
Who made it, my Lord? What did your Lord tell him? So he says:
Here is my Lord, truly, and He has treated me well, as He was raised on.
The selection remained and the choice was better for him when he brought me out
From prison, he did not say, "Put me in prison, I will be polite with you."
God brought me out of prison and brought you from
البدو وبعد كده التربيه الثانيه من بعد ان
Satan has stirred up trouble between me and my brothers. Indeed, my Lord is Kind.
Whenever He wills, He is the sign. He is the sign. He is the sign.
The All-Knowing, the All-Wise, my Lord, You have given me sovereignty
And you taught me from what he teaches you, and you taught me from interpretation.
Hadiths and verses only
In short
The first episode: How Joseph, peace be upon him, was made
Educational and doctrinal benefits of faith. I ask God for them.
If we have achieved the intended purpose
Verses date, God willing we will meet again
The coming is good, may God benefit us and you, and may we hear
Glory be to You, O God, our Lord, and praise be to You. I bear witness that there is no god
You asked forgiveness, may peace and mercy be upon you.